Arizona Dranes Okeh Records Correspondence, 1926-2004, bulk 1926-1929 SC 135
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Arizona Dranes Okeh Records Correspondence
1926-2004
1926-1929
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Dranes, Arizona
Consolidated Music Publishing House
SC 135
1 document case 0.21 linear feet
The collection consists primarily of contracts and correspondence between Arizona Dranes and the Consolidated Music Publishing House (owner of the Chicago OKeh Records franchise) from 1926-1929. Contracts for Nov. 15, 1926, include one song not commercially released (and possibly not recorded), "He's Got Better Things for You." Also included are articles about Dranes and this collection by the donor, Malcolm Shaw, and gospel historian Dr. Daniel E. Walker.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series:
Series 1: Contracts
Series 2: Correspondence
Series 3: Related Articles
Biographical / Historical
Arizona Juanita Dranes was the first recorded African American female gospel pianist and singer. Born ca. 1894 in Dallas, Texas, she recorded a series of groundbreaking gospel records in Chicago between 1926-1928 for the OKeh label. Dranes, who was apparently born blind, combined southern barrel-house style piano with a sanctified style of singing. Her many health problems, combined with the economics of the depression, contributed to the demise of her brief recording career. She remained active within the Church of God in Christ, the largest African American Pentecostal denomination and producer of such acts as Sister Rosetta Tharpe, Edwin and Walter Hawkins, and Andrae Crouch. Initially a Fort Worth-based pianist for Bishop Samuel M. Crouch, she also assisted F. W. McGee and other COGIC leaders, and toured with Katie Bell Nubin and her daughter, Sister Rosetta Tharpe. In her later years she moved to Los Angeles where she died on July 27, 1963.
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2004 by Malcolm Shaw.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of contracts and correspondence between Arizona Dranes and the Consolidated Music Publishing House (owner of the Chicago OKeh Records franchise) from 1926-1929. Contracts for Nov. 15, 1926, include one song not commercially released (and possibly not recorded), "He's Got Better Things for You." Also included are articles about Dranes and this collection by the donor, Malcolm Shaw, and gospel historian Dr. Daniel E. Walker.
African American gospel singers; African American musicians--Biography; African American women musicians; Business correspondence; Contracts; Sound recording industry; Bradford, George; Consolidated Music Publishing House (Chicago); Consolidated Talking Machine Company; Consolidated Theatrical & Musical Exchange; Crouch, Samuel M., 1896-1976; Fearn, E.A.; General Phonograph Corporation; McGee, F.W.; OKeh Records (Firm); Rockwell, Thomas G., 1901-1958; Shaw, Malcolm; Walker, Daniel E.
- 1. Contracts, 1926-1929; 15 Items
  - Contract, Consolidated Theatrical & Musical Exchange, Chicago (E.A. Fearn, Manager) and A. Dranes, [1926?]; 1 document 3 typed leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Contract, General Phonograph Corporation, New York, and A. Dranes, for "indefinite" period, June 1, 1926; 1 document 2 typed leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contracts, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes works recorded June 17, 1926, 6 documents 6 leaves (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "It's Alright Now", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "In That Day", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "John Said He Saw The Holy Number", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "My Soul Is A Witness For The Lord", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "Sweet Heaven Is My Home", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "The Crucifixion", June 17, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes works recorded November 15, 1926, 5 documents 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "I'm Glad The Lord Saved Me", November 15, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "Bye And Bye We're Going To See The King", November 15, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "Lambs Blood Has Washed Me Clean", November 15, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "He's Got Better Things For You", November 15, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract, Consolidated Music Publishing House, for A. Dranes recording "I'm Going Home On The Morning Train", November 15, 1926; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Consolidated Talking Machine Company, record of Cash Advances to A. Dranes, 1928-1929; 2 documents 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Consolidated Talking Machine Company record of cash advance to A. Dranes, September 7, 1928; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Consolidated Talking Machine Company record of cash advances to A. Dranes, September 2, 1928-March 12, 1929; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 2. Correspondence, 1926-1929; 49 Items
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, offer to record for Okeh in Chicago, May 4, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dranes to Mr. Bradford, seeking clarification of recording offer, May 26, 1926; 1 document 3 manuscript leaves (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, detailing arrangements for test pressing, June 4, 1926; 1 document 2 typed leaves (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dranes to Consolidated Talking Machine Co., regarding arrival in Chicago on Sante Fe line, June 13, 1926; 1 document 1 telegram (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dranes to C.T.M. Co. regarding contract, accompanied by letter of recommendation from pastor, June 23, 1926; 1 document 2 typed leaves (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, concerning status of test pressings and expenses, July 10, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf; 2 receipts (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dranes to C.T.M. Co. concerning receipts, July 16, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf with stamped cover (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, soliciting her assistance with publicity and distribution, July 20, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes regarding record sales, radio appearances, and contracts, August 19, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes regarding record sales, reimbursements, and promotions, August 20, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dranes to C.T.M. Co., regarding current and future releases, August 31, 1926; 1 document 1 ms. leaf (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, regarding future releases and recording works by other composers, September 4, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dranes to George Bradley [sic] requesting advance, September 6, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - [George Bradford?] to Dranes regarding advance, September 9, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Geo. Bradford to Dranes regarding November recording sessions, October 8, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dranes to C.T.M. Co. regarding contract and train fare to Chicago, October 25, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [E.A. Fearn?] to Dranes, regarding travel and accomodations for trip to Chicago, October 27, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dranes to Consolidated Talking Machine Co. regarding travel plans, November 2-5, 1926; 2 Items (1 typed leaf + 1 telegram) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dranes to Consolidated Talking Machine Co. regarding travel plans, November 2, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Western Union telegram from Dranes to Consolidated Talking Machine Co. regarding travel plans, November 5, 1926; 1 document 1 telegram (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dranes to George Bradford regarding illness and opinion of recordings, December 17, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Consolidated Music Publishing House to Dranes regarding contract and royalties, January 28, 1927; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dranes to Geo. Bradford requesting contract, February 12, 1927; 1 document 1 ms. leaf (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dranes to Geo. Bradford regarding lack of royalites, February 17, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [C. T. M. Co.?] to Dranes regarding Okeh sessions in Memphis produced by [Tommy] Rockwell, February 22, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fern [sic] regarding visit from [Rockwell?] and illness that prevented recording, February 28, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fearn regarding receipt of payment and records, and inquiry regarding F. W. McGee, March 12, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - C.T.M. Co. to Dranes regarding Rev. F.W. McGee and future recording session, March 16, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fearn regarding future recording session, April 20, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - C.T.M. Co. to Dranes regarding arrangements for future recording session, May 15, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - C.T.M. Co. to Dranes regarding arrangements for recording session in Chicago, June 8, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fearn regarding future recording session and expiration of contract, June 14, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - C.T.M. Co. to Rev. Samuel Crouch (Ft. Worth) regarding whereabouts of Drane, June 15, 1928; 1 document 1 telegram (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - E.A. Fearn to Dranes regarding arrangements for travel to Chicago, June 22, 1928; 5 Items (1 telegram + 3 receipts + 1 business card) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Postal Telegraph-Commercial Cables telegram from E.A. Fearn to Dranes regarding arrangements for travel to Chicago, June 22, 1928; 1 document 1 telegram (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Record of cash wired to A. Dranes, June 22, 1928; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Missouri Pacific Lines confirmation of cash advanced by Consolidated Talking Machine Company for Dranes travel from Sherman, TX to Chicago, IL, June 22, 1928; 1 receipt (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Business card of E.V. Hartung of Missouri Pacific Lines, June 22, 1928; 1 document 1 business card (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Postal Telegraph-Commercial Cables receipt for money order from E.A. Fearn to Dranes, June 22, 1928; 1 receipt (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fearn regarding return to Oklahoma City, July 26, 1928; 1 document 1 ms. leaf (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - C.T.M. Co. to Dranes regarding delayed payment, August 4, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dranes to E.A. Fearn notifying him she is in Chicago and requesting meeting, August 6, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - E.A. Fearn to Dranes regarding payments and advances, August 10, 1926; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dranes (OK City) to E. A. Fearn, about payments to session musicians, August 11, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Dranes (Chicago) to E.A. Fearn, requesting advance, November 7, 1928; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dranes (Memphis) to Fearn requesting copies of last two records and a Victrola, February 28, 1929; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - E.A. Fearn to Dranes (Memphis) regarding mailing her latest record, March 11, 1929; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous address information for Dranes, 1928-1929; 4 Items (2 postcards + 2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Postcard from A. Dranes to E.A. Fearn with change of address information, October 12, 1928; 1 postcard (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Postcard from A. Dranes to E.A. Fearn with travel address information, January 1, 1929; 1 postcard (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Handwritten note with permanent and temporary addresses for Dranes, July 10, 1928; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Handwritten note with address for Dranes, September 7, 1928; 1 document 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 46)
- 3. Related Articles, 1970-2004; 2 Items
  - "Arizona Dranes & Okeh," by Malcolm Shaw (Storyville 27, Feb./March 1970), 1970-02-01-1970-03-31; 1 document 5 photocopied leaves (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Arizona Dranes biography, by Daniel Walker (AAAMC Liner Notes article), 2004; 1 document 1 typed leaf (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Liner Notes, No. 9 Online (PDF)
    https://aaamc.indiana.edu/liner-notes-pdfs/linernotes9.pdf